<?xml version="1.1" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<constitution xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
              xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="../schemas/constitution.xsd"
              version="0" created="2025-05-08" pullRequest="1">
	<body>
		<preamble>
			<p>
				This Constitution establishes the Organizational Architecture of the <b><i>TerraModulus Project</i></b>
				as the foundational framework governing the superior Realm for the entire Project,
				administrating the Community, supervising the Projects and Policies,
				moderating the Rules and Regulations,
				and executing the Elements and Procedures for the entire Organizational Architecture.
			</p>
		</preamble>
		<article title="Structures and Establishment">
			<content>
				<p>
					The Governing System consists of Governing Bodies and Governing Executive Systems.
					Execution Framework Proposals (EFPs) are Proposals which make decisions and operate procedures;
					Executive Policy Charters (EPCs) are Charters which settle Policies, Rules and Regulations;
					Executive Research Dossiers (ERDs) are Dossiers which Governing Researches shall be made.
				</p>
				<p>
					On the whole, Governing Executive Systems maintain their own Roles and Purposes without overlaps;
					and one may hierarchize the other; specific definitions shall be made in corresponding Charters.
				</p>
				<p>
					A Proposal or a Charter may directly inherit another one from another Governing System,
					when both Systems share the same mandatory features and functionalities;
					in an inheritance, alignments of Things to this System shall be declared in the same Proposal.
				</p>
				<p>
					Executive Directives (EDs) shall be initiated by a Governing Board for provisional or
					possibly permanent executions for the Governing System.
				</p>
				<p>
					Community Standards and Guidelines (CSG) include selections from EPCs for public reference
					to applicable Rules and Regulations for the Community;
					Execution Standards Compilation (ESC) includes selections from EFPs for public reference
					to available Standards and Specifications for the Projects.
				</p>
				<p>
					This Constitution and underlying Governing Systems shall uphold the supreme authority.
				</p>
				<p>
					Jurisdiction of this Constitution shall always be covered under international regulations.
					All acts in local areas shall also be covered under respective local jurisdictions.
				</p>
			</content>
		</article>
		<article title="Governing Bodies">
			<content>
				<p>
					Members of the Bodies hold Roles in Governance of this Constitution,
					with certain obligations and liabilities depending on their Powers and Permissions.
				</p>
				<p>
					The Bodies hold authority over this Constitution.
				</p>
				<p>
					The Host Organization of this Constitution holds supreme authority via a Governing Board.
				</p>
			</content>
			<section title="Governing Board">
				<content>
					<p>
						A Governing Board oversees and guides the Governing Council for administration and operation.
					</p>
					<p>
						An Executive Leadership holds authority over the Executives.
						The Executive Leadership shall be decided by the Host Organization of this Constitution
						without participation of Community.
					</p>
					<p>
						An optional Chief Governance Officer may be appointed to cooperate with the Leadership
						in ensuring compliance with this Constitution and underlying Proposals and Charters.
					</p>
					<p>
						Within this Board, a Supreme Governing Group shall be formed jointly by an Executive Leadership
						and a Chief Governance Officer;
						amendments and interpretations of this Constitution must be approved by Supreme Governing Group.
					</p>
				</content>
			</section>
			<section title="Governing Council">
				<content>
					<p>
						A Governing Council discusses and votes Proposals being drafted or passed.
					</p>
					<p>
						The Council oversee the Community by Process of Proposals.
					</p>
				</content>
			</section>
			<section title="Governing Executive Committee">
				<content>
					<p>
						A Governing Executive Committee supervises the Governing Council.
					</p>
					<p>
						Members of the Committee shall be elected and appointed from the Council.
					</p>
					<p>
						The Committee may also discuss Proposals during discussions in the Council.
					</p>
					<p>
						The Committee votes passed Proposals by the Council for Ratification,
						which accords to the results of voting in the Council.
					</p>
				</content>
			</section>
		</article>
		<article title="Directorial Branch">
			<content>
				<p>
					Most governing acts by the Governing Bodies are under the Directorial Branch.
				</p>
			</content>
			<section title="Process of Proposals">
				<content>
					<p>
						Proposals are the primary Executive operations in Governance,
						objectively driven by the Community.
					</p>
					<p>
						Execution Framework Proposals (EFPs) are formal procedures to Executions in this Constitution;
						they may provide standards, methods, and structured execution plans,
						including but not limited to strategies, projects, guidelines and advice.
					</p>
					<p>
						In the Executive and Governing levels, Proposals shall
						outline how a project, procedure or initiative will be executed, managed, and monitored
						to achieve its objectives, or,
						explain or define a certain mechanism which would be applied onto this Constitution, or,
						behave as a governing procedure for other purposes of Proposals.
					</p>
					<p>
						Any Participant or Member of this Constitution maintain the Rights to initiate Proposals,
						which shall potentially make changes to or affect any Part of the entire Architecture.
					</p>
					<p>
						A Proposal may potentially represent stances of the Governing Bodies or the overall Project
						by any means regardless.
					</p>
					<p>
						A Proposal to initiations or amendments to a Charter shall be proposed via this Process;
						a submission of the corresponding Charter must be enclosed jointly for Process of Charters;
						the body of Proposal of Charter must only contain non-normative information to the Charter
						while the main, normative body of the Charter remains in the main file of it.
					</p>
					<p>
						A Proposal to initiations to a Research Dossier shall be proposed via this Process;
						the Proposal shall optionally appoint Members of the Community for the Research Dossier.
					</p>
					<p>
						Whenever a Proposal being Standards and Specifications for the Project,
						it shall be submitted to Execution Standards Compilation (ESC).
					</p>
				</content>
			</section>
			<section title="Process of Charters">
				<content>
					<p>
						Executive Policy Charters (EPCs) are formal authoritative forms of
						Policies, Rules and Regulations in this Constitution;
						they shall be led by Governing Bodies;
						they may also establish organizational principles, governance structures, and policies.
					</p>
					<p>
						Charters may be iterated by versions in different Streams of Charters.
					</p>
					<p>
						Whenever a Charter being Policies, Rules and Regulations for the Community,
						it shall be submitted to Community Standards and Guidelines (CSG).
					</p>
					<p>
						All Participants and Members shall adhere to the Charters whenever
						their designated administrative scope and obligations are applicable.
					</p>
				</content>
			</section>
			<section title="Executive Directives">
				<content>
					<p>
						When an Executive Directive (ED) is proposed by the Governing Board, it shall be self-ratified.
					</p>
					<p>
						Whenever a Directive affects this Constitution, a Proposal or a Charter,
						a definite time limit must be declared; otherwise, the limit may be omitted.
					</p>
					<p>
						In most cases, a Directive shall not affect this Constitution.
					</p>
				</content>
			</section>
		</article>
		<article title="Managerial Branch">
			<content>
				<p>
					The Managerial Branch is responsible for administrative operations in this Constitution.
				</p>
				<p>
					Community Moderators may be elected from the Community and appointed by the Governing Bodies
					to aid in moderation of the Community.
				</p>
			</content>
		</article>
		<article title="Investigative Branch">
			<content>
				<p>
					Appointed members and voluntary participants shall conduct researches and investigations
					as per a corresponding ratified Executive Research Dossier (ERD).
				</p>
			</content>
			<section title="Process of Research Dossiers">
				<content>
					<p>
						Executive Research Dossiers (ERDs) are structured summaries or compilations of
						research findings, insights, and recommendations to provide high-level overviews of
						research foundations, and shall provide suggestions and advice to governing operations.
					</p>
					<p>
						Research Dossiers are filed by Topics of Researches, sequential by stages or times in Streams.
					</p>
				</content>
			</section>
		</article>
		<article title="Participation of Community">
			<content>
				<p>
					All Members of the Community have the rights to supervise the Governing Bodies
					through participation and discussion in administrative activities.
				</p>
				<p>
					In cases of dereliction of duty by the Governing Bodies,
					the Community may challenge individuals through corresponding procedures defined in Charters.
				</p>
			</content>
		</article>
		<article title="Amendment Process">
			<content>
				<p>
					This Constitution shall be amended only by extraordinary consensus for Ratification from
					the Supreme Governing Group.
				</p>
				<p>
					The Governing Council, whenever Members shall deem it necessary, shall propose an iterated Version
					of this Constitution with all Amendments to be made in a Version.
				</p>
			</content>
		</article>
		<article title="Archival and Transparency">
			<content>
				<p>
					All governing resources such as iterations of this Constitution and the Executive Systems,
					must preserve historical versions for transparency.
					All amendments and archives must be publicly documented.
				</p>
			</content>
		</article>
	</body>
</constitution>
